<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Blog on Daniel Hacks It</title>
    <link>https://danielhacks.it/blog/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Blog on Daniel Hacks It</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.147.5</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 15 Jun 2025 15:00:43 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://danielhacks.it/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Sine Synthesis with FPGA</title>
      <link>https://danielhacks.it/blog/20250608_sine_synthesis_on_fpga/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Jun 2025 15:00:43 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://danielhacks.it/blog/20250608_sine_synthesis_on_fpga/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last time we did together a circuit using verilog to communicate to a I2S device. But we never delved into how to make a waveform for it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, don&amp;rsquo;t get me wrong: if you did the blinky led example while starting your first projects, this can be easily achievable for you:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A square pattern is just zeros and ones&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A saw pattern is a counter from zero to max&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A triangle wave is a counter that goes back after hitting max or min values&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A sine wave is just some &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/CORDIC&#34;&gt;CORDIC&lt;/a&gt;&amp;hellip;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, we will not be using CORDIC and will not be doing simple counters. I want to show you a couple of tricks to generate a clean sine waveform that you can later compose to create more fancy sounds.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Digital audio with I2S</title>
      <link>https://danielhacks.it/blog/20250608_digital_audio_with_i2s/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Jun 2025 14:12:26 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://danielhacks.it/blog/20250608_digital_audio_with_i2s/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you perhaps know, I&amp;rsquo;m working on this blog also as a way to log my learning journey. So, to support the lack of interesting peripherals on the Arty A7, I bought a set of modules for Arduino. Most of them quite uninteresting, but I got this I2S DAC module from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.adafruit.com/product/3678&#34;&gt;Adafruit&lt;/a&gt; that implements the UDA1334A from NXP (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nxp.com/docs/en/data-sheet/UDA1334ATS.pdf&#34;&gt;datasheet&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This device interest me the most among the ones I got from the assortment, because since I was a kid I wanted to make my own guitar effects (in fact, I believe many electronic engineers are born this way or similar), so the end goal is quite ambitious as you can see. But let&amp;rsquo;s start from something easy.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>UART: the basics after you know the very basics</title>
      <link>https://danielhacks.it/blog/20250529_uart_for_practice/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 17:12:23 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://danielhacks.it/blog/20250529_uart_for_practice/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, after you are done with the book and implemented your first 8-bit CPU you keep wondering&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ok, but now I want to do real world stuff&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here I got you back, nothing comes before when it comes to real world stuff that having the capability of sending data to/from other devices. When I began my personal projects, when I got my Arty A7, I thought that I needed to be able to debug what&amp;rsquo;s happening inside the FPGA when the internal logic analyzer might not be too reliable (pro-tip: it&amp;rsquo;s very reliable). So being able to send to a computer data using a simple protocol is a must.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What Is HDL? The explanation you did not requested</title>
      <link>https://danielhacks.it/blog/20250527_what-is-hdl/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 May 2025 16:43:31 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://danielhacks.it/blog/20250527_what-is-hdl/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are a hardware engineer you need no explanation though, this is more for the programming guys who attempt to make things with an FPGA in the belief that is the next step of Arduino (I do think that though, so no judgment made here)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As someone who wrote a lot of code in my young age (still loving fiddling with Linux kernel), I&amp;rsquo;m lucky I got the purpose of HDL.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Blog introduction</title>
      <link>https://danielhacks.it/blog/20250525_introduction/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://danielhacks.it/blog/20250525_introduction/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Let me be brief, as this is just to fill the emptyness of a newly created blog: I want to learn new skills and take notes that can be shared with people in the hope they will find useful as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this blog I have the plan to showcase my personal projects on electronics and perhaps other fields, maybe adding some of the knowledge I have accumulated in the last years in the field (if it doesn&amp;rsquo;t break any NDA, of course).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
